Athena is the goddess of war and combat strategy, but also of the wisdom,
ability, sciences, and justice. She was one of the twelve principal deities that
lived at the Mount Olympus, and her name comes from the Greek term Ἀθῆναι that means "divine intelligence"
or "ethical intelligence".
There are several theories about her origin, the most extended says that her father was the same, Zeus.
His first wife Metis, a Titaness, prophesied that their children would be
more powerful than their own father. When she got pregnant he, scared, decided to swallow her.
Even though, she gave birth and Athena was born from Zeus' forehead with
Hephaestus' help, the god of fire and metals
who let her get out with his ax.
Others tell that she was Pallas' daughter, the titan of wisdom. When he tried to abuse her
she killed him and the skin to make her a breastplate,
the Égida and she put the wings in her feet. Even she was considered Poseidon's daughter,
god of seas, she got mad with him and she was adopted by Zeus.
The unique thing that's clear is that her heart is closed for passions. She never had a husband or lover
and she was known as "Athena the virgin" or Athena Parthenos, where the name
of the most famous temple dedicated to her comes from, the Parthenon on the Acropolis.
That's where it was a huge statue of her of 12 meters of height, built
by Fidias. Unlike other goddesses, she was represented always dressed,
with a long tunica and the Égida on her chest.
Like the goddess of war and protector of heroes, she usually wears a helmet above
the forehead to show her pacific face. In one hand she carries goldenrod, with which she gives
protection to her favorites. And on the other hand she carries her shield with the head of the gorgon, Medusa,
gift of the hero Perseus for helped him to defeat her. She's usually accompanied by an owl,
a bird that then became philosophy's symbol.
Other times, she carries a snake on her lap or her feet. It comes from the myth in which
she became Erichthonius' adoptive mother and protector, the first king of Athens,
born of Hephaestus and Gaia. One day, she put him into a little basket and entrusted it to three of her sisters.
She didn't say what it had, but she warned them about don't open it until she came back. But couldn't
avoid it, and to their horror, they found the kid turned
into a snake.
When Erichthonius became the founder of Ancient Greece's capital,
Athena competed with Poseidon to be the city's protector, still without a name. Poseidon
hit the ground with his trident, making appear a salty water fountain, and Athena
planted an olive. Zeus decided that the tree had appeared first, choosing Athena
as patron of the city, named in her honor.
Another version tells that the Athenians voted to choose one of the gods. The women
voted for Athena and the men for Poseidon. She won by only one vote,
and the god of the seas, angry, flooded the region. To calm his anger,
women's right to vote was removed.
Athena helped with the state's prosperity, encouraging the agriculture con the invention
of the plow and the rake. She also taught the men to tame the beasts and to produce fire.
And not only, but they are also attributed to her several inventions related to science and art
like the numbers, the navigation, the sewing, and even some instruments
like the flute or the trumpet.
As the city's protector, she protected it from foreign enemies, exercising as a warrior goddess,
but in a different way than Ares'. She did not even have weapons, she took them to borrow from Zeus,
and she never sacrificed uselessly her soldiers. She didn't love war
and she only supported the more favorable battles.
She also was a great advisor for a lot of classic heroes. She taught Heracles
how to flay the Nemea's lion using its own claws to cut its thick skin.
She also helped him to kill the Lerna's hydra.
During the Trojan War she was with greeks, and after the battle helped Ulysses
telling him what he had to do to recover his wife Penelope and his kingdom. In the fable
of Jason and the Argonauts, she's the one who teaches to the builders of the ship "Argo".
Today, Athena still has a big relevance. Her statue appears in a lot of government buildings
of America and Europe, like the Vienna Parliament. And also in so many coins,
like the American one of 50 dollars of 1915,
the most valuable one of its history.
Athena has so many myths and stories that we could be hours talking about her.
But we would like to talk about so many other gods, tiktakers.
Ask us for your favorite ones at the comments!